A Guide to the Library of Virginia Video Collection, 1979-1997
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia Video Collection, 1979-1997
The Library of Virginia
44284
17 DVDs (1 box)
Included are the Library of Virginia building dedications, significant conferences and speakers sponsored by the Library, as well as footage of noteworthy events including the Phillip-Morris sponsored nationwide tour showcasing Virginia's ratification copy of the United States Bill of Rights. The collection originated, in part, from the Library of Virginia circulating collection.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
For preservation purposes, patrons should use digital access copies of original recordings.
Acquisition Information
In-house transfer from the Acquisitions and Access Management Division.
Scope and Content
Collection, 1979-1997, of videorecordings that document various programs, activities, and events supporting the mission of the Library of Virginia. The recordings also document important issues challenging Virginia libraries. The recordings span the years 1979-1997 and include the groundbreaking and dedication ceremonies for the new Library of Virginia building at 800 East Broad Street and the dedication ceremony for the Virginia Authors Room. Featured speakers include Governor Douglas Wilder, Rita Dove, William Styron, and George Allen. Television interviews with Library of Virginia staff on "Virginia Legislature...This Week" and "This Week in Richmond" featuring State Librarian of Virginia Nolan Yelich and Deputy Director, Sandy Treadway. Topics include the opening of the State Library building, The Dictionary of Virginia Biography project, State Library publication "Cavalcade," and researching women's history. Additional footage in the collection includes the 1990 Governors Conference on Library and Information Services and footage of the 1990 VLIN conference held at the Sweet Briar Institute. Conference speakers include Clifford Lynch, Tom Wolfe, Governor John Dalton, and Mary Hatwood Futrell. Also included are promotional spots and a documentary of the Phillip-Morris sponsored nationwide tour showcasing Virginia's ratification copy of the United States Bill of Rights.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series 1: Special events and staff interviews
Series 2: Library conference recordings
Series 3: Miscellaneous video
Contents List
- Library of Virginia Video Collection, 1979-1997., Extent: 17 DVDs.
  - Special events and staff interviews 1993-1997. (Box 1)
    - Virginia State Library and Archives: New Library Building Official Groundbreaking. 8 September 1993., 90 min. (Disc LVAVC001)
      Groundbreaking ceremony for the Virginia State Library and Archives. Featuring speeches by Gov. Douglas Wilder, State Sen. Ball, and hosted by Peggy Forehand.
    - Library of Virginia: New Library formal dedication ceremony. 16 May 1997., 78 mins. (Disc LVAVC002)
      Various speakers are: Charles McDowell, Peter James Lee, Nolan T. Yelich, Viola O. Baskerville, Thomas W. Moss, Stanley C. Walker, John W. Carlin, Andrew H. McCutcheon, Margaret Forehand Stillman, Rita F. Dove, John H. Chichester, George Allen, and Benjamin W. Robertson.
    - The Virginia Author's Room at the Library of Virginia: dedication program with special guest William Styron. 6 November 1997., 70 min. (Disc LVAVC003)
      Guest speakers include: William Styron, James L.W. West, III, Marcy Sims, Nolan Yelich, Serf L. Guerra, John Cole, Beverly Sgro, Francis Foster and Beverly Bagan.
    - WRIC This Week in Richmond: Opening of the new State Library building. 1996., 29 min. (Disc LVAVC004)
      A weekly public television talk show focusing on Richmond, Virginia news and events. State Librarian, Nolan Yelich, and Deputy State Librarian, Sandy Treadway, discuss the new state library building under construction at 800 East Broad Street in Richmond, Va.
    - Virginia Legislature...This Week: Dictionary of Virginia Biography. n.d., 28 min. (Disc LVAVC004)
      A weekly public television talk show about Virginia government and legislative issues and programs including topics of general interest. John Kneebone and Brent Tarter discuss the plans and scope of the Dictionary of Virginia Biography project.
    - Virginia Legislature...This Week: Virginia Cavalcade n.d., 29 min. (Disc LVAVC005)
      A weekly public television talk show about Virginia government and legislative issues and programs including topics of general interest. Kip Campbell and Stacy Moore discuss the Library of Virginia historical publication "Virginia Cavalcade."
    - Virginia Legislature...This Week: Researching women's history n.d., 28 min. (Disc LVAVC005)
      A weekly public television talk show about Virginia government and legislative issues and programs including topics of general interest. Library of Virginia deputy director and historian, Sandy Treadway, discusses Women's history topics and research.
  - Library conference video, 1979, 1990, 1993. (Box 1)
    Governor's Conference on Library and Information Services, State Reading workshop, and VLIN conferences.
    - Governors Conference on Library and Information Services. Richmond, Virginia. 17 April 1979.
      - Governors Conference on Libraries, 17 April 1979. (Disc LVAVC006)
        Highlights of conference. speakers and interviews include Tom Wolfe, Gov. John Dalton, Mrs. Virginius Shackelford Jr., State Librarian Donald Haynes.
    - Governor's Conference on Library and Information Services. Richmond, Virginia. 10-11 November 1990,.
      - Governor's Conference on Library and Information Services, 10-11 November 1990., 30 min. (Disc LVAVC006)
        Conference speaker, Mary Hatwood Futrell.
      - Governor's Conference on Library and Information Services 10-11 November 1990., 30 min. (Disc LVAVC006)
        Conference speaker, the Honorable Mayera E. Oberndorf (Mayor of Virginia Beach, Virginia),
      - Governor's Conference on Library and Information Services 10-11 November 1990., 60 min. (Disc LVAVC006)
        Conference speakers include Ann Heidbreder Eastman, John C. Tyson, John C. Casteen III,
      - Governor's Conference on Library and Information Services promotional video. 10-11 November 1990., 6 min. (Disc LVAVC006)
        promotional spot featuring Governor Doug Wilder
      - Governor's Conference on Library and Information Services: Va. 10-11 November 1990., 30 min. (Disc LVAVC007)
        Conference speaker, Virginia Secretary of Education James W. Dyke Jr.
    - Conference on Libraries and Economic Development, 1996.
      - Conference on Libraries and Economic Development: Conference footage, 1993., 300 mins. (Disc LVAVC008)
        Conference sponsored by the Virginia State Library and Archives and the Virginia Dept. of Economic Development discussing economic development and its impact on libraries and the formation of the Virginia Library Information Network and its effect within the library community. Held at the Radisson in Richmond, Va.
    - State Library Reading Workshop 1996.
      - State Library Reading Workshop - Morning Session, 1996., 87 min. (Disc LVAVC009)
      - State Library Reading Workshop - Afternoon Session, 1996., 190 min. (Disc LVAVC010)
    - Virginia Library and Information Network (VLIN) conferences and teleconferences1994.
      chronological
      - Virginia Library and Information Network Leadership Institute - Sweet Briar #1 12 October 1991., 76 min. (Disc LVAVC011)
        Leadership conference held at Sweet Briar College discuss issues facing Virginia libraries and future plans for VLIN in Virginia.
      - Sweet Briar #2: Clifford Lynch 12 October 1991., 61 min. (Disc LVAVC012)
        Leadership conference held at Sweet Briar College to discuss issues facing Virginia libraries and future plans for VLIN in Virginia. Guest Speaker, Clifford Lynch.
      - Sweet Briar #3 12 October 1991., 113 min. (Disc LVAVC013)
        Leadership conference held at Sweet Briar College to discuss issues facing Virginia libraries and future plans for VLIN in Virginia.
      - VLIN Phase II: The Future of VLIN - Teleconference 7 June 1994., 150 min. (Disc LVAVC014)
        Clifford Lynch discusses via teleconference the future of VLIN; then his comments are discussed by a panel of librarians led by Patricia Wilson Berger.
  - Miscellaneous videos 1991-1997. (Box 1)
    - Bill of Rights 200th anniversary retrospective presented by Phillip Morris. 1991., 16 min. (Disc LVAVC015)
      Documentary on the 1989 U.S. Bill or Rights 200th anniversary nationwide tour sponsored by Phillip Morris. Virginia's ratification copy was toured.
    - U.S. Bill of Rights tour promotional spots 1991., 9 min. (Disc LVAVC015)
      Nine commercial spots to promote Phillip Morris' sponsorship of the U.S. Bill of Rights 200th anniversary tour. Created by Ogilvy and Mather advertising.
    - Let us save what remains: a presentation of the Virginia Sate Library and Archives. 1991., 14 min. (Disc LVAVC016)
      Documentary on the value of archives in preserving history through conservation of documents.
    - Shine Up Your Words: A Morning With Rita Dove. 1994., 58 min. (Disc LVAVC017)
      Poet Rita Dove speaks to children on poetry and the value of words